A Guide to the Amanda DeHart Collection, 1901-2010
Christiansburg Institute Museum and Archives
Christiansburg Institute Museum and Archives
Amanda DeHart Collection, 1901-2010
Christiansburg Institute Museum and Archives, Christiansburg Institute, Inc.
MS2020-03
19.5 linear ft. 6 Boxes
Amanda DeHart; Christiansburg Industrial Institute
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Amanda DeHart collected and organized this collection as Historian for the Christiansburg Institute Alumni Association.
Biographical Note
Amanda E. DeHart attended Calfee Training School in Pulaski, Va., and graduated from Christiansburg Industrial institute in 1942. She received her B.S. degree from St. Paul's College of Lawrenceville, Va., in 1948 and then became a teacher at CII from 1952-1966 teaching cosmetology. In 1976, Amanda DeHart and other former students formed the Christiansburg Institute Alumni Association. In 1988, Mrs. DeHart donated her papers to Virginia State University, many of which document the History of African American Education in Southwest Virginia. In 1991, Amanda DeHart authored a definitive history of the school, Christiansburg Institute: A Proud Heritage with James W. Smith, professor of History at Virginia State University. Mrs. DeHart was the historian and Archivist for the Christiansburg Alumni Association and her papers follow her arrangement.
Scope and Content
The Amanda DeHart Collection contains records about Christiansburg Industrial Institute (C.I.I.) and border African American life in Southwest Virginia. DeHart collected materials as a student, teacher, and alumni of C.I.I. Included are DeHart's research for Christiansburg Institute: A Proud Heritage, photographs of the school and nearby communities, artifacts of student life, and records that document the activities of the Christiansburg Institute Alumni Association (C.I.A.A.). The collection is a mixture of original documents and photocopies.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged with respect to Amanda DeHart's original filing order.
Publication Note
Smith, J. W., & DeHart, A. E. (1991). Christiansburg Institute: A proud heritage. Petersburg, Va: Westar Pub. Co.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Amanda E. DeHart Papers, Accession #1988-61, Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University, Petersburg, VA.
Index Terms
Subjects:
African Americans--Education--Virginia--Christiansburg--History; African Americans--Virginia--Montgomery County--Biography; African Americans--Virginia--Montgomery County--History; African Americans--Virginia--Pulaski County--History; Christiansburg Industrial Institute--History; Montgomery County (Va.)--Biography
Contents List
- Series 1: Personal Papers
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 1)
  - United Methodist Services/Religious Papers (Folder 2)
  - Gardening (Folder 3)
- Series 2: Photographs, 1940-2001
  - Subseries 1: Elliston photographs, 1950-1980
    - Goldie Scott Crocket photographs, c.1950 (Folder 1)
    - Elliston Baptist Church, undated (Folder 2)
    - Photo Album #1, 1950-1980 (Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Virginia Tech Events, 1997-2001
    - Theta Delta Chi Cleanup, c.2000 (Folder 4)
    - Service Learning Events, c.1997 (Folder 5)
    - Virginia Tech Black Cultural Center, undated (Folder 6)
    - A Century of Contribution, Virginia Tech, 2001 (Folder 7)
  - Subseries 3: C.I.A.A. events, 1974-2002
    - Indoor Yard Sale, 1988-1999 (Folder 8)
    - Cemetery Restoration, undated (Folder 9)
    - Cooking Around the World, 2002 (Folder 10)
    - Museum Visits, 1997 (Folder 11)
    - Tillman Sease Banquet Program, 1974 (Folder 12)
    - C.I.A.A.- Roanoke Chapter, 1999 (Folder 13)
    - Schaeffer Memorial Baptist Church Yearbook, 1989 (Folder 14)
    - Principals’ Cemetery, 1997 (Folder 15)
    - A Proud Heritage book jacket draft, c.1990 (Folder 16)
  - Subseries 4: Christiansburg Industrial Institute, 1940-1980
    - C.I. class photo with Principal Walker, c.1940 (Folder 5)
    - Photo Album #1, 1950-1980 (Folder 8)
    - Elaine Carter Photographs, c.1940-1960 (Folder 13)
    - C.I.I. Class Photos, 1950-1951 (Folder 16)
    - Christiansburg Institute book cover, c.1960 (Folder 17)
- Series 3: Christiansburg Industrial Institute, 1901-1999
  - Subseries 1: Scrapbooks, 1935-1940
    - Elizabeth Toliver, Class of 1937, autograph book (Folder 1)
    - Amanda DeHart 5th grade scrapbook, c.1940 (Folder 2)
    - Virginia R. Lynch, Class of 1935, autograph book (Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Newspaper articles, 1943-1999
    - Newspaper articles, 1943-1999 (Folder 1)
  - Subseries 3: Friends’ Freedmen’s Association, 1880-1930
    - Friends’ Freedmen’s Association, 1880-1930 (Folder 1)
  - Subseries 4: Christiansburg Institute Administrative Documents, 1901-1963
    - Graduation ephemera (Folder 1)
    - C.I.I. published serials, 1901-1931 (Folder 2)
    - C.I.I. programs, 1935-1951 (Folder 3)
  - Subseries 5: Christiansburg Institute Alumni Association, 1976-1999
    - Minutes, 1976-1982 (Folder 1)
    - Reunion Materials, 1980 (Folder 2)
    - Newsletters and Programs, 1977-1990 (Folder 3)
  - Subseries 6: Correspondence, 1976-1999
    - Correspondence, 1976-1999 (Folder 1)
- Series 4: Media, 1947-2010
  - Subseries 1: New River Valley Publications, 1981-2004
    - Historical summaries, 1981-2004 (Folder 1)
    - Closure and sale of C.I., 1951-1995 (Folder 2)
    - New River Valley Current Sunday, March 18, 2007 (Folder 3)
    - (Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: Ebony Magazines, September 1963-May 1968
    - Ebony Magazines, September 1963-May 1968 (Folder 1)
  - Subseries 3: Miscellaneous, 1988, undated
    - Miscellaneous, 1988, undated (Folder 1)
- Series 5: Pulaski County History, 1919-1990
  - Subseries 1: Calfee Training School, 1928
    - Photographs, 1928 (Folder 1)
    - Calfee Junior Pioneer (student publication), 1945-1946 (Folder 2)
    - Educational exercises, 1919-1924 (Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Pulaski County, VA Newspaper Clippings, 1921-1990
- Series 6: Oversized Collection, 1977-1999
  - Subseries 1: Personal, 1985-1999
    - Gem City Gardening Club scrapbook, 1985-1990
    - Graduates of C.I.I. (sketches) (Book 1)
    - History and Sketches of Historic Events (Book 2)
    - Media History (Book 3)
    - Sketches and Media (Book 4)
    - Black History, Printed Media, Sketches (Book 5)
    - (Sketchbook 1)
  - Subseries 2: Miscellaneous, 1977, undated
    - C.I.I. Campus maps and blueprints reproductions (Folder 1)
    - Posters (Folder 2)
    - C.I.A.A. Reunion poster, 1977 (Folder 3)
    - Photo display (Folder 4)